alright okay so three I think today I'll
just go with a an oldie but a goodie one
that I've been before but I think it's
useful to have this in its own specific
frame so today what I'll do is I'll run
through the Kineton framework from
Dean's snow that identifies the
distinction between three qualitatively
different kinds of system and how we
might go about responding to those
different kinds of systems okay so to
begin the the first kind of system is
complicated a complicated system is
defined by the fact that the phase space
which is a concept that refers to the
tonal possible states that the system
might occupy total possibilities that
might occur within the system the total
phase space of a complicated system is
finite and bounded which means that
whether it's small like say the
relatively simple space of a tic-tac-toe
game which only has a handful of number
of different kinds of ways that came to
be played or very large like say the
phase space of a Boeing 777 it is
broadly speaking unchanging and for
related reasons causation the
relationship between cause and effect in
complicated systems is largely clear and
therefore predictable so what happens
when you're in a complicated system say
for example you're dealing with
tic-tac-toe is that the appropriate
approach is to to see how much of that
face space how much of the central
states the system you can in fact grasp
with precision if it's a simple system
like tic-tac-toe
then you can grasp all of it in which
case the appropriate response is to
simply identify with clarity exactly
what the outcomes
a beach move and then execute would be a
perfect approach if the complicated
system is too large for that kind of
approach
say for example again our Boeing 777
where it's sort of impossible for anyone
to endeavor to grasp in its totality
nonetheless one can become an expert and
develop a lot of skill in predicting how
it will respond to different inputs and
outputs because remember the end of the
day it's finite and bounded and with the
properly constructed crew of experts we
can affect go about managing that system
very effectively and efficiently whether
we're talking about building one or
maintaining one this is fine and that's
more or less what our civilization is
very good at doing it's very good at
partitioning identifying complicated
systems and then beginning the
construction of three levels of
sophistication in crews of experts and
them energy this brings us to a complex
systems so we're a complicated system is
defined by the fact that its phase space
is finite and bounded and that the
relationship between cause and effect is
clear and predictable a complex space is
kind of the opposite wishes to say that
its phase space is about the States that
it can occupy are themselves changing
the kinds of states that it can occupy
are changing so it's a phase space is
unbounded and as a consequence infinite
and for oolitic reasons the relationship
between cause and effect in a complex
system is unclear
it is difficult and sometimes in fact
close to impossible to predict the way
that the system will respond to a given
input this does not mean however their
complex system can't be dealt with
effectively it just requires a different
approach and so the appropriate approach
to a complex system is to learn how to
be responsive to its disposition
while you cannot predict and while cause
and effect are unclear in complex
systems you do have correlations
it has probabilities that can be
identified with some level of confidence
it has a disposition and while this
disposition is going to drift if you
become skillful at having sensitivity to
the subtle signals of the system and
become skillful in exploring the state
and the space and the drift of the
complex system then you can respond to
it effectively or more precisely
adaptively
and this is the right way to respond to
a complex system for me the economical
example here is circuit you're surfing
you're dealing with a highly complex
system the wind the state of the water
or the temperature the water the
direction of the waves the intensity of
the winds the feedback between all these
different things on each other the kind
of board that you have the weight of the
board your weight the way that you're
paddling your distribution of weight on
the board and these are so many
different feedback loops that the
relationship between cause and effect is
very unclear and things are changing
culling there's no two times
there's no way to surf the same wave
twice nonetheless with a appropriate
amount of experience and practice you
can build a capacity to become a very
skillful surfer and achieve something
that would be properly termed beautiful
and then this brings us to chaos if in
complication the relationship between
cause and effect is clear and
predictable and in complexity we have it
is unclear and yet we have dispositions
when we finally get to chaos we find
ourselves in a circumstance where even
dispositions go away and that in effect
in a chaotic system we have no basis for
making good choices so it's actually
easier to
jump to the example here we can imagine
that we're on one of those enormous
waves that Laird Hamilton made famous
and without knowing or willy-nilly we
find ourselves swept under by the wave
deep underwater twisted ahead of her
tail bubbles everywhere and it's
effectively pitch-black so this is chaos
we have no idea which way is up and if
we were to endeavor to swim to what we
may think is up we're just as likely to
be swimming down or towards the rocks as
we are towards the Serbs and even if I
may to the surface we may find might
find ourselves still in the middle of
the whitewater and phone chaos we can't
actually yet make a good choice and so
the way that one responds to chaos is to
wait to slow down to conserve your
capacity to respond if and when the
system transitions back into complexity
go limp conserve your energy and wait
and when you then notice that perhaps
light is up and the bubbles are all kind
of going in the same direction towards
the light you've transitioned back into
a complex space and you can begin to
redeploy your stillness in this case to
swim to the surface and that's pretty
much it
so we have complicated complex chaotic
we have finite bounded clear causation
predictable results appropriately met by
expertise inclusive experts that can
manage complicated we have dispositions
we have subtle signals we have
experimentation and exploration in the
construction of an adaptive capacity in
complexity and then we have weighting
being in a little
space listening becoming very subtle
listening and allowing a chaotic space
to transform back into complex space
that's all I hope that this particular
concept proves useful